Don't let people tell you that it can't
be done. [music] When they tell you it
can't be done, it's because they can't
do it.
>> This is Anders Hilesberg, the creator of
Typescript and C. And we talked about
how Typescript recently became [music]
10 times faster through a native
rewrite.
>> Couldn't we like fix JavaScript? [music]
Wouldn't that be better? [laughter]
Do you know what I mean?
>> If you think about Rust, what didn't it
have that if it had it, you would have
picked it?
>> I mean, I think there are two things.
[music] Um, if you're going to hand AI
the keys, I mean, then all bets are off,
right?
>> Why is there such a big difference
between this opinion and what I see from
maybe people who work at Anthropic?
People love these like take it all the
way to 100%. [music] Right? And that's
where I get off the bus.
>> Here's the full episode.
The big thing that we're going to talk
about here is obviously TypeScript 7
with the native rewrite. And the first
thing that I think of when I see this
was I didn't even realize that the
compiler was written in JavaScript to
begin with because I don't usually think
of compilers being written in you know
highle dynamic languages.
>> Yeah. No.
>> So why was Typescript written originally
the compiler written in JavaScript?
>> No, it's a good question. Uh, and
honestly, if you had told me like before
the TypeScript project started that
Anders you're going to be writing
compilers in JavaScript, I'm like, "No,
no, I'm not." But I mean it it it you
know the original prototypes for for
TypeScript um the Strata project as it
was called in the in the very early days
was actually written in C because it was
like an adapt adaptation of the the
parser the JavaScript parser that we had
in IE and whatever and and then we moved
to to JavaScript but we wrote it sort of
C style. Um but why did why did we go
with JavaScript? Well, I mean, if you
can self-host in the ecosystem that you
want to be a part of, then that is just
dramatically better than putting
yourself outside the ecosystem and
trying to target that ecosystem. Do you
know what I mean? Because by writing it
in Typescript, we were also
daily users of Typescript and daily
users of the tooling that we were
building. And whenever something didn't
work right, we knew it immediately. And
whenever something didn't perform right,
we knew it, you know. And so so in the
early in the early years, it was it was
a huge uh boon I think. And then of
course
JavaScript runs everywhere, right? And
that meant automatically our compiler
could run on every platform anywhere
even in the browser right uh had we gone
with a native code solution at that time
it wouldn't have been possible to run it
in the browser. Now we have web assembly
or wom you know but that didn't exist at
the time right um so so it was it was a
meaningful choice uh and honestly
at that time also people didn't really
realize how fast JavaScript had gotten I
mean it used to be very slow and then
Google did all of their excellent work
with V8 and got it to within two or 3x
of of native code which is pretty darn
impressive. Um, and it was like full
well possible to write compilers in in
JavaScript. Um, and you could even get
them performant. Uh, because often
it's the algorithms that determine how
performant you are. It isn't necessarily
the runtime environment, right? I mean,
it's a combo, but but yeah.
>> Is there anything unique about the
TypeScript compiler? like you know I
think of a compiler I think of clang or
or you know one of those ones that is
used for maybe C, C++ or those static
languages. What's unique about the
TypeScript compiler when it was written
in JavaScript compared to these native
uh compilers?
>> I think there are a couple of things
that are pretty unique about
TypeScript's compiler. First of all, it
doesn't target machine code. targets
JavaScript [laughter]
and and some people call that a
transpiler and in a sense you know the
the compilation phase is mostly about
removing the type annotations and
turning your TypeScript back into
JavaScript. Right now in the early days
also an important part of of the
compilation process was to downlevel
your JavaScript meaning
all of the runtime environments at the
time were not evergreen. uh and
sometimes people were lagging like
multiple years behind on which level of
the standard was implemented and for
example when classes got standardized
most JavaScript runtimes didn't
implement classes but it turns out that
you can downlevel to constructor
functions and and trans transform the
code and so part of what we did was this
transformation down level transpiling of
the code but then of course the type
checking uh is is the big thing that we
loop and the type checker in in
Typescript is also quite unlike any
other type checker uh in other
compilers. Typically type checkers exist
in compilers to guide the code generator
um because you want to know are we
dealing with a float or an in or a
string here so we can generate you know
the correct machine instructions for
that data type etc etc. That's not the
case in in Typescript. In fact, since we
erased the types, the types have no
impact whatsoever on the runtime
behavior of the code. They purely exist
for for tooling sake and for the
developer sake and to guide things like
statement completion and refactoring and
code navigation, which is a whole
different thing. Um, and also they don't
necessarily have to be there. Uh, and so
Typescript has a gradual type system.
you can sort of have half of your code
have types and the other half is just
any um that we don't check. Now very few
languages have anything like that. So,
so it's very it's a very different
compiler in in in that sense, you know,
and a very different language in in that
sense. Um, that actually made it
fascinating to work on because we were
solving problems that no one had solved
before, you know.
>> I know a lot of compilers, you know,
they take the the higher level code and
they typically apply optimizations as
well. Maybe, you know, they unroll loops
or they get rid of duplicate
instructions, simplify things. Is
anything like that happen in the
TypeScript to Java compilation process?
>> Very little. Um, like I said, when we do
the down leveling, there there's some
transformations that that that go on
that are that are complex, but it is
less and less the thing that's important
about Typescript. And in fact, a lot of
people use TypeScript only for the type
checker. uh and then they use some
bundler like ESB build or SWC or
whatever to package their app, erase the
types, do whatever needs to be done in
order to make it runnable in in in the
browser. And so we're not really there
to optimize your your code for runtime.
We're there to make you more productive
as a developer or make AI more
productive as a as a developer.
So with the the native rewrite of this
originally fully JavaScript compiler,
what was the problem you were trying to
solve with the rewrite and why did you
end up write rewriting it in native
code?
>> Well, I mean the the problem we were
trying to solve it's real simple
performance and scalability. JavaScript
was never really optimized for compute
inensive workloads like compilers,
right? JavaScript is more about creating
UI that runs in a browser. Was
originally intended for just like maybe
a 100 lines of code, but now of course
it's gotten to be a lot more. Um, but
it's not it's not a place that that you
would optimize for um for the kind of
workload that that we are. So in
JavaScript, first of all, you pay a 2 to
3x perf penalty compared to native code.
I mean it depends on on the workload you
know but that's but if if you're doing
compute that's about where it's at. Um
and then secondly in JavaScript there
are a lot of restrictions around use of
concurrency. Uh JavaScript was always
engineered in fact to be a single
threaded language. That's why we have
callbacks and async and and and
whatever. It's because you can't spin up
threads. Um, and that's a good thing
mostly because concurrency in a language
with mutable data is very very hard
because you can have races and deadlocks
and all of this good stuff, right?
That's why functional programming
languages are easier with concurrency
because all the data is immutable and
it's much easier to reason about. Um
so JavaScript doesn't give you access to
concurrency other than web workers and
but web workers can't share data between
each other other than by remoting it. So
you can you can have one web worker
compute some something, but if it wants
to give it to some other web worker, it
has to turn it into JSON or it can't
just hand it objects. And that means you
can't have one worker compute some data
structure and then have someone else use
it. In other words, you can't have
shared memory concurrency. And really
that's what we wanted in order to gain
all of the perf that we were leaving on
the table by not utilizing multi-core
CPUs that everyone has today, right?
Because Moors law has stopped giving us
faster CPUs. It's giving us more CPUs
and we got to like find ways to use them
in our in our compute intensive
workloads or else we're leaving money on
the table. And so we were leaving money
on the table in multiple ways, right?
And so native code and that was why we
we looked for a language that
would get us out of both of those binds.
It had to be native and it had to have
access to shared memory concurrency.
>> I saw for the language choice you went
with Go. And when I think of all the
systems languages, the ones that are
often hot or maybe you know Rust or
Zigg, why did you choose Go for the
native rewrite? I think the decision
process was actually pretty structured.
You know, the first decision we made was
we're not going to rewrite. We're going
to port because only by porting can we
preserve the semantics and the
algorithms and the exact behavior of our
existing compiler which everyone depends
on for backwards compatibility. Now we
could have we could have cleaned the
slate and started completely from
scratch but we would have come we would
have come up with a different language
in the sense that it would give you
different errors or behave differently
in certain situations where it has to
make choices between multiple
possibilities and and what have you.
Right? So we wanted to port and that
meant our code makes certain assumptions
like our code for example assumes the
existence of garbage collection. It
assumes the existence of first class um
uh treatment of functions. You know, you
can have functions within functions and
you can close over over out of state and
so forth. Um and as we evaluated all of
these,
Go was was the one that checked the most
boxes. You know, it gives us it gives us
very robust and mature native code
generation on all major platforms. it
has garbage collection and it has access
excellent access to shared memory
concurrency. Um, and those were like the
high order bits that we wanted to check
and every other language had something
that kind of worked against those
objectives. So for this particular
workload, Go was the right was the right
choice for us and it's worked out well.
>> If you think about Rusk, what didn't it
have that if it had it, you would have
picked it? I mean I think there are
there are there are two things um it
doesn't have uh garbage collection
it's done manually you know uh well or
it's done through the borrow checker but
the borrow checker doesn't allow
circular data structures and our
compiler is chalk full of circular data
structures we have trees with parent
pointers we have types that are
recursive we have symbols that refer I
mean it's everywhere and like I said if
we had chosen to rewrite we could have
probably solved all of that, but it
wouldn't have been just porting the
code. It would also have been like
solving a whole bunch of new problems
that we had bought ourselves by by going
that route. We tried [laughter]
and it just wasn't feasible, you know,
uh and and and so so we were we were
just trying to optimize for, you know,
doing as little work as possible to get
us to the payout, which is which and
honestly, Rust is no better when it
comes to like the quality of the
generated code or the or the the
concurrency gains that we could have
gotten out of it.
Go just as it's great. I mean, so so we
got we got all the bennies with for less
work by by going that route.
>> I know some languages they're when you
say they're garbage collected, they
>> there's something in the the language
itself that is doing garbage collection,
but um there's also independent
libraries that can provide garbage
collection, right?
There is, but it it but it comes often
with a whole bunch of restrictions and
and and it doesn't come necessarily with
the safety guarantees that we were
looking for. I mean, like Go is type
safe and memory safe. uh meaning that
you don't get to just like have stray
pointers or or whatever where Rust you
can do ref counting or you can do you
can do all sorts of different strategies
but there's always like that little bit
of unsafe where you have to like do this
in order to make it all work you know uh
where where if garbage collection is
engineered into the language it really
is a a separate concern that is you you
you don't you don't have to do anything
special in I mean of course you you have
to like not hold on to data that you no
longer need and whatever you know but
that's true of ref counting as well
right but but it is inherent in in the
language
when you ported it from JavaScript to go
I'm curious how much LLMs were used in
that process because I know famously
there's some major projects that have
been doing uh rewrites of their entire
codebase I know there's this JavaScript
project called bun
>> that rewrote everything from Zigg into
Rust and so
>> seems like a pretty useful tactic and
I'm curious if you leverage that in this
process.
>> Not a whole lot but it also has to do
with timing. Uh we started this project
two years ago and two years ago LLMs
were nowhere near as good as they are
now. I mean that's how crazy fast it
it's all moved, right? Um,
so what we did though is we we certainly
had
a bunch of tools that aided us in the in
the in the the port. I'd say the
prototypes we wrote, the scanner and the
parser we wrote manually. Um, and at
that point we could convince ourselves,
wow, we can actually get 10x out of
this. Now what do we do with the rest of
this codebase? And what we did was we
wrote a tool that syntactically
translates TypeScript into Go.
This Go that comes out of it, it has no
syntax errors in it, but it doesn't
compile either because it's full of, you
know, like it uses types as if they were
TypeScript, which they're not in Go. And
so all of that had to be refactored. We
had to redo all the data structures or
whatever, but we got the same code base
out of it. And then we can sort of bang
on that. and then in a more localized
fashion maybe use AI occasionally to
help us do the transformation. So it was
sort of manual and automated
and a little bit of AI. Now if we were
to start the project today would we do
it differently? Possibly. Um although I
will say if if we just let AI loose on
you know what is it like half a million
lines of code that we have in the old
compiler or somewhere between half a
million and a million right uh and asked
it to translate it all. Well I don't
know that that would absolve us from
then having go in and carefully
examining every line that came out of it
to make sure that there were no
hallucinations. Right? Unless you have
100% perfect test coverage, you probably
still got to go check all of that. Now I
think a a a better approach quite
honestly would be enlist AI to write a
program that helps you translate from
Typescript to Go because at that point
you can park the stochasticness in that
program and then you can get
deterministic behavior whenever you run
the program which means you get the same
transformation every time you run it
right that's always the thing about AI
that people forget it's not
deterministic right so you can't really
trust that it's going to do the same
thing twice.
Um, [snorts]
so, so we might have done it that way,
but AI was not ready to do it at the
time. Now, that doesn't mean that we
don't use AI. I mean, like now down the
line, we use AI a lot in our in our
internal processes around like the the
compiler as everyone does, right? Like
help it to write tests and to move pull
requests and what what what have you.
and and whenever an issue is logged, we
first thing we do is put copilot on and
see if it can fix it for us, right? I
mean, and so yeah,
>> in that approach where you you use the
LM to generate uh tooling and then you
know the tooling is deterministic,
>> but you'd still have to validate that
thing.
>> Yes. But that's that's a lot smaller
surface area that you have to validate,
right? And honestly, I I've seen that
even with friends that are like we did
some trip together and there was like
some some accounting of they go, well,
he paid for the hotel rooms or we paid
for this and whatever and we needed to
like sort it all out, right? And so, so,
okay, well, here's what all the costs
were and here were the pie and like have
AI fix it for us, right? Or like tell
who owes who what and it very
authoritatively came up with the wrong
answer, right? [laughter]
Because it just forgot like about some
of the settlements, right? And but if we
had asked it to write a spreadsheet,
which is really that's just a program,
right? Then we would have gotten the
right answer because it's very good at
writing programs. So it's kind of funny
how you you you don't sometimes you you
don't ask AI for the for the answer. You
ask it for a program that computes the
answer.
>> What are the potential benefits that you
left on the table by doing a port
instead of a full rewrite?
>> To be honest, I don't think there are
any. Um, and I don't think we would
consider uh a rewrite. We were quite
happy we're quite happy with the way
this codebase works. Uh, and we're and
we certainly I don't think we're leaving
any any money on the on the table
currently. Um, and and as I said
earlier, rewrites are toxic often for
ecosystems because they sacrifice
compatibility because you never rewrite
and you get you never get back to
exactly what you had before, right? Oh,
but oh, but in the name of making it
better or prettier or whatever, we
change this and that and this and that
and the other, right? And then well, all
the users get to suffer through that,
right? So, so backwards compatibility is
super important if you want to keep your
ecosystem happy. Uh, and and and we we
do want that. [laughter]
In studying for this interview, I I just
keep reading about JavaScript and the
the strange semantics of the language.
And I think throughout my career too,
people have typically
not been super satisfied or happy with
JavaScript for some reason or the other,
>> right?
>> And my question is why is it so popular
despite that?
>> So first of all, I I don't think
JavaScript is as bad of a lang of a
language as as some people make it out
to be. I I I will say in in like the
three about three four weeks that
Brendan Ike had to create this language
back in the mid 90s, he did a lot of
things right. Um and thank God that he
had been educated on functional
programming and and got first class
functions done right where you can have
functions within functions and the inner
functions can access the outer function
state and you can pass functions around
as first class values.
that is super powerful and JavaScript
actually got that very right. Um, now
there's some quirks in the language too,
like all of the automatic conversions
and all of the bizarre differences
between double equals and triple equals
are just like drives everyone mad,
right? But that's exactly what type
checkers are happy to do. They can like
they can far it out all the little
differences because they understand the
all the deep semantics of the language
that no one seems to be able to keep in
their mind, right? So, and I think
that's part of why Typescript has become
so popular, right? It's like it can
actually like truly bring out the best
parts of JavaScript uh and leave the bad
stuff behind. And of course, you can't
like like the thing about JavaScript is
it is the crossplatform language. Like
even Java that was engineered and
intended to be the way to write
crossplatform applications, it's not
really crossplatform. It doesn't run in
the browser, you I mean it doesn't it
doesn't run everywhere, right?
JavaScript runs everywhere. Um, so there
are a lot of there are a lot of reasons
why you should like JavaScript and and
with TypeScript, I think we've managed
to sort of capture all the badness and
park it.
I saw there were some projects. I don't
know if you're familiar with Dart or
CoffeeScript and
>> it seems like these were some effort to
replace JavaScript or improve it and
>> right
>> but they're not popular today. So I'm
curious what happened.
>> I mean I think coffecript was mostly
it's a different syntax for JavaScript.
So, so it doesn't really change the the
semantics and it doesn't it didn't
provide any additional tooling and and
whatever. And and Dart was also in a
sense about fixing JavaScript, right?
But if you can fix something by fixing
it instead of trying to replace it with
something else, then you're doing the
ecosystem a much bigger favor, I think.
Right. And that's what we set out to do
with TypeScript. We weren't trying to
change JavaScript. we were trying to
improve JavaScript. Um, and I think
that's ultimately why we why we
succeeded.
>> I mean, in this new age where it's very
feasible that maybe AI could rewrite
code bases,
um, I imagine people will start to go
towards the the desired languages rather
than the ones that are the incumbent
languages.
And I'm curious if you think that
JavaScript might become less used in the
future.
>> See, I I don't think so. I I what I've
observed is that AI
is best at the languages if seen the
most of in its training set, right? And
AI gets trained on all the code that
exists in the world. Um,
which means there's an awful lot of
JavaScript, an awful lot of TypeScript,
an awful lot of Python. And therefore,
AI is good at JavaScript and TypeScript
and Python. And it is less good at my
favorite little language that I just
invented. In fact, there's none of it in
the training set, which means you have
to sacrifice God knows how many tokens
in the prompt to teach AI the language
before you can even ask it a question
about the language. Do you know what I
mean? So in that sense I think incumbent
languages are actually if anything going
to flourish uh because of AI and we're
sort of seeing that right now with with
TypeScript too right there there's a
noticeable knee in the curve of
TypeScript adoption that coincides with
the advent of AI. I do think the
incumbent languages are actually if
anything getting stronger.
>> What percent of all JavaScript is
written in Typescript?
Well, so, so in the last year,
Typescript uh became the number one used
language on GitHub. Um, so there's
JavaScript more than JavaScript.
>> So, so more than 50% on GitHub at least
>> is is is written in in Typescript. Um,
so so we're actually like larger now
than the language that we set out to
improve.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. And larger than Python. If you
were to just draw that out in the
future, do you think that eventually
TypeScript would become the default and
almost 100% of all JavaScript would be
typed?
>> Well, certainly, I mean, if you're
having AI write it, I I almost challenge
you to find a tool that writes
JavaScript. They all write TypeScript.
Uh because it helps AI write better code
because the type annotations guide the
LLM towards writing or to write making
fewer mistakes. and the ability for us
to statically validate the code before
you run it. I mean, that's the
distinction, right? The only way you can
validate JavaScript is by running it,
which means you have to set up a runtime
environment, which might not be possible
for AI to do because AI lives in a
sandbox, right? But AI can run through
tools, the compiler, and check the code
that it just generated and be told, "Oh,
you made a mistake. Oh, well, let me fix
it then before I even tell anyone that I
made the mistake, right? [laughter]
[snorts]
>> After learning about the this 10x
improvement in performance from uh
rewriting in native, I makes me wonder
why anyone would use JavaScript on the
back end. Why not just always use native
languages on the back end?
>> Well, it depends on your problem. Uh I
think because the thing that that
overlooks is
what kind of thing am I going to write
on the back end, you know, like like
there are an awful lot of very very good
web server frameworks for example that
that use TypeScript or JavaScript,
right? So, so if there are like
frameworks in your ecosystem that gets
you to a solution quicker than if you
had to write that because your native
language wasn't really intended to
target that particular community. So, I
think it very much depends on
your what what your problem is
affinitized with. Um, and and often PF
of your code isn't the bottleneck. I
mean, like look at Python. I mean right
it's it's used to basically script and
all of the LLM training in in the world
right I mean which clearly a lot of that
code is ultra timer critical uh but
that's written in native code right and
then you use Python as the orchestration
language and in a sense in a web server
you know like TypeScript is just an
orchestrator you know of talking to a
database and doing this and that what
and and and the things that the things
that that ultimately control the
performance of applications like that
aren't necessarily
whether that inner for loop is running
as as as native code or not which
actually it is because of the JIT anyway
right I mean so
I mean measure measure first and then
make decisions right because you always
get surprised when you measure
>> when you talk about how much faster it
was too one of my immediate thoughts is
why wasn't it done sooner
>> you know at the time we started
TypeScript script. I don't know that we
had ever envisioned that people would be
writing projects that are the size of
the projects that people are now writing
in Typescript, right? Like Visual Studio
Code is like 2.3 million lines of code.
I mean, we have in in-house projects
that are over 10 million lines of of of
code, which is insanity. We would have
just at the time gone, well, that's
clearly no one's ever going to do that,
right? But that was a decade ago or more
than a decade ago, right? We started in
2012 with the TypeScript project and the
world looked very different and so
gradually people have started writing
larger and larger and larger projects,
right? And at the same time, our
compiler has gotten smarter and smarter.
We've added all sorts of cool features
like union types and discriminated
unions and control flow analysis and
blah blah blah. And all of these things
make our type checking even better, but
it also makes it go a little slower
every time we add a new feature. Right?
In fact, our TypeScript 6 runs only
about 50% of the speed of TypeScript 1.5
for example. But TypeScript 1.5 also did
a whole lot less. Um, so projects have
gotten bigger and the compiler does
more. All of which [laughter]
detract from your effective output. And
as I mentioned, Mors law also
unfortunately stopped delivering faster
CPUs and JavaScript keeps you from
taking advantage of the additional
cores. And it's not clear that we could
have foreseen all of that, right? But
but but it's just the way it panned out,
right? [snorts]
>> Open AAI, Enthropic, Curser, and
Verscell all use this product to make
their lives better. And the problem it
solves is when you're building SAS or an
AI product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's skim, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So let's say you have a new SAS
product and you want to sell to other
companies. work OS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you. You
can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. Jira by
Atlassian isn't just for tracking work
anymore. Now you can pick your favorite
AI agent to assign tasks to and they'll
get access to the rich context that's
already in Jira. When the agent is done,
it surfaces a pull request. That way you
can get more done with your favorite
agents all in one place. Learn more at
jira.dev. That's jir.dev.
Appreciate them for sponsoring the
podcast. And back to the show. When I
first became a software engineer and I I
went to start working at Facebook at the
time, they had this popular framework
called Flow, which was
>> doing type inference on top of
JavaScript. It was this thing that would
take a long time.
>> Yep. And then I' I'd never hear about it
these days. So it sounds like Typescript
won if there was a competition to
typing.
>> There was a bit of it. Yeah. In in in
the early days. Um I think the thing
that worked for us was actually the fact
that we were self-hosted which made it a
lot easier for the community to
contribute to the project. [snorts]
Flow was written as I recall in camel.
Um, and so in order to contribute to
flow, you had to go learn a whole
different way of programming and and in
a in a different language, right? And
Float also didn't really focus all that
much on
IDE based tooling,
which we knew full well going in. We're
writing a compiler, but we're not
writing a compiler in order to generate
machine code. We're writing it to make
better tooling. That was why we wrote
it, you know, and so right there
handinhand with our compiler, we had a
language service. It was deeply
integrated into Visual Studio, Visual
Studio Code, all sorts of other editors
through an open protocol, you know, and
that just that's where that was the
problem that needed solving, right? I
mean, it's not it's it's nice to have a
type checker, but boy, you you want
that. You also want statement
completion. You wanted red squiggies.
You want like I mean, you want it
interactive, right?
So I know in your career you've you've
worked on uh multiple programming
languages. What does it take to build a
programming language? Well, first I'll
say that the world needs another
programming language like it needs
another hole in the head. I mean it it's
it's like you you kind of got to be a
certain [laughter] kind of of person to
to even embark on it to begin with,
right? It's a super fascinating area of
of computer science and it's one that's
been around ever since the beginning of
of of computers. Now, every compiler,
every language has a whole bunch of
things you need to to understand like
parsers and scanners and lexers and code
generators and and and and whatever,
right? But but that's sort of the
mechanics of implementing the language.
And then there's the design of the of
the language, sort of the art of making
it feel right and whatever, right? And I
I think you sort of have to master both.
And then you also got to appreciate that
like every new language is actually only
10% new and then it's 90% the same
drudgery that every other language has
to go do. And so be prepared for a lot
of work that maybe isn't as interesting,
you know.
And then finally maybe I'll say that you
know like never forget there that you
you stand on the shoulders of giants. I
mean you you in order to make a great
programming language you got to
understand a bunch of other programming
languages first uh and understand all
the all the distinctions between the
different styles of programming like
procedural and object-oriented or
functional or what have you. Um
and then last but not least it's like
it's a long game. I mean, it is probably
a longer game than anything else. I
mean, like every language project I've
worked on, I've worked on each of them
for at least 10 years. Um, and shipped
multiple versions, and it's really never
until version three that it truly starts
to get okay. Do you know what I mean?
And, and it just takes an incredible
amount of devotion to to that. So, you
got to really not be the type that tires
of a problem quickly and then moves
along. that you're not meant to do
language design.
And you see that too if when you talk to
language designers in the industry,
they've been doing it for a long time.
>> You mentioned those two parts. There's
the the objective pieces that you need
to implement and then there's the the
art of the design and making the
language I guess ergonomic for
developers. When you think of that
second part, that art
>> and you look at other programming
languages, are there any that you admire
outside of the ones that you've worked
on? Of course,
>> learning and and and fully appreciating
the beauty of functional programming has
has been very educational, right? I
mean, because it really is a different
way of thinking about programming, a way
of thinking of programming that's much
closer to math than it is to
machines. Um,
and I think there's there's a lot of uh
incredible goodness that has come from
that. And and honestly even in in like
like building the TypeScript project uh
large portions of the TypeScript
compiler are written in a highly
functional style um and work on
immutable data structures that are then
now because of shared memory concurrency
can be shared between different
uh threads or processes that don't
mutate the data and therefore they can
share one data structure. Right? And
that's incredibly powerful. But
mastering this, you know, like writing
islands of pure functional programming
inside an imperative program and ma and
and and putting it together with
concurrency. I mean, it's it's it's
complex, but I think functional
programming has brought a lot to the
world. Um, I know object-oriented
programming as well. I mean, but I
wouldn't single out any particular
language. Every one language you you
come in contact with, you learn
something. You know,
>> you mentioned the world doesn't really
need more programming languages and uh
if you think 10 years from now, do you
think there'll be less programming
languages than there are today?
>> It's hard to say. I mean, but like I
said,
AI tends to favor the incumbents, right?
And I I do think and I I think this has
been true even before AI. The bar keeps
going up for what it takes to
successfully implement a programming
language and create an ecosystem around
it. I mean it used to be oh you just
need a compiler.
Well
you also kind of need tooling now. I
mean you need a language service you
need uh you need debuggers. You need
profilers. You need frameworks and
libraries. You need code generators that
can target all sorts of I mean it's like
it just keeps getting harder and harder
uh you know to to to get all the way
there.
>> Well, when you think about all those
pieces that really they're all for the
people or I mean the you know the IDE
and the types and I mean the the
computer looks at that too but it's so
that we can read source.
Maybe one day the LMS will generate
machine code directly. I wonder. Um
I think
I think LLMs are better at what they do
when when they don't have to repeat
themselves a lot. I I I think like
when a program is expressed in text, it
is closest to its sort of ultimate
condensed meaning and representation,
right? If you translate it into machine
code, there's an awful lot of noise in
that machine code. Like all of the
instructions, like half of the
instructions are memory addresses that
have absolutely no bearing on what's
going on here, right? So half of it,
half of all the data is noise already,
right? And then whichever register you
pick, well, that doesn't matter either
in the code generator. And honestly, you
could change your mind at any point in
time. So, so teasing the truth out of
that noise is a lot harder than if you
just have a program where the variable
is called I and whatever. And by the
way, that you can relate to the written
instruction that the user just gave you.
I mean, keep in mind that that like AI
are they're just emulators of humans in
a sense, right? I mean, they they it's
like neural networks, right? There's a
reason we have programming languages
because we're terrible at writing
machine code straight off. out of our
head, right? AI is not that different
from us, you know? So, the same would
probably be true there. when you look
back on working on C and you know
TypeScript and these language projects
they were long journeys and I think you
know one thing people might want to know
is what did you learn through those
journeys that if you knew at the
beginning of when you embarked on
working on them you you might have been
better off
gosh well each journey is is different
uh I mean like the first project I
worked on turbo Pascal. I I think
that project started back in the old
days when it was 8-bit micros and 64k of
memory and one person could do
everything themselves and have ultimate
control of everything. And so I was very
much a one-man shop, right? But that
quickly was not scalable, right? And and
and capacities of machines. So we went
for 64 to 640K and then then kaboom the
the the the lid went off, right? and you
could have as much memory as you wanted
and so not one person couldn't do it and
I had to learn to become a team player
right and that that was a big journey
for me I mean to learn to let go right
if you're a perfectionist that that that
could be hard but that's one thing that
I would say I learned there
>> well another way to word this question
is you know what's the most common
mistake that you see people make when
they embark on building a programming
language
Well, I think people tend to overindex
on one idea, you know, that that they
have that they think, "Oh, wouldn't it
be cool if my language could do blah,
and then they underindex on all of the
mundane stuff that every programming
language has to do, you know, and then
it ends up doing that one thing they
love maybe better, but then it does
everything else not as good." [laughter]
And and and the net is a detractor,
right? And so it's so hard to convey how
many things you have to do that really
doesn't have anything to do with the
problem you're you're trying to solve
per se, you know, when you're
implementing programming languages.
>> And when you were working on C, do you
keep tabs on the other languages and
>> you know what they're doing better, what
you could do better with C?
>> Yeah. No, you got to keep yourself
informed about because like I said, we
all stand on the shoulders of giants,
you know, no other no programming
language was ever created in in in
perfect isolation, right? Everyone
learns from from everyone and then
someone comes up with a good idea and
then you see it adopted elsewhere and
we've adopted many ideas from functional
programming you know in C for example
and then other languages have adopted
some of the good ideas we had in C# like
async you know now is in JavaScript and
in some of the other programming
languages out there and that was
pioneered in C and so you know it's it's
we all learn from each other um and and
that's how the industry moves forward
really You mentioned the I guess
learning to let go. I think that's
something that a lot of people as their
career advances they they start with you
know individual contributor work and
then later they start delegating things.
>> How did you learn that or what was the
is there like a maybe a story or
particular project where you you let go
and you you kind of develop that skill?
Well, it's it's almost like I got a
counter story to the to the letting
letting go there because in the C
project um my main function was not
implementing the the C# compiler. It was
being the language designer and writing
the spec and designing all the new
language features. And
before that when I when I had worked on
Turbo Pascal, I was I was doing a bunch
of active coding, you know, on on the
thing itself, right? But then I sort of
let go of that. But I let go of it too
much and I sort of drifted up into the
stratosphere and became more of an
architecture astronaut. Do you know what
I mean? And and and I wasn't getting my
hands dirty. I was writing stuff in the
framework and in the libraries, but it
was it didn't quite these are not like
the deep really super hard problems to
solve, right? And and I didn't really
know it at the time, but I was gradually
getting less happy with with the work
that I was that I was doing, right? I
mean, it's I still enjoy, but there was
something missing, right? And so when
when this TypeScript opportunity came
along, I decided to jump in and actually
actively participating writing compiler
and it brought so much happiness to my
life. Like I I I I finally realized I'm
just I'm just a happy coder, you know? I
mean, I like the spec stuff too, but but
coding is like, man, that's what gets me
up in the morning, make coffee, and
write some code, you know? That's that's
that's that's when I'm my in in my happy
space, you know.
you know, when people are at these
really really high levels, they're kind
of have this expectation of a certain
level of impact. And so, how do you
continue to write code at as such a high
level engineer?
>> Well, the specific code I'm writing
isn't necessarily having all all that
impact, but it's it's the fact that I
also do the architectural guidance, you
know, as part of a a group of people,
right? in a in a project, you know,
there's plenty of work for everyone to
go around and then you you just but you
you you stay involved in a corner of the
project because then you see what
happens in the code, you know, when
you're checking in your code, you go,
what was what what was that over there?
Let let me just what what's happening
over here, you know, or or you realize,
oh, we need to refactor this. This this
is not this is not feeling right
anymore. Or if if but if you let go of
that you don't really you can't really
talk about the thing that people use
day-to-day. You can talk about the
syntax of the thing that people use
day-to-day but you can't talk about that
thing you know so
so both are important I think and I'm
happy that I get to do both now I know a
lot of companies have this idea of
engineering archetypes or the the way
that highle engineers get some work done
and you mentioned architect for instance
a lot of companies have different words
for architect I'm not sure if you're
saying it's just your working style or
are you saying that all high level
engineers should be hands-on at some
level.
>> No, I I'm not saying that because I
don't think it's it's like I made a
conscious choice to
remain an independent uh contributor as
opposed to become a manager. I mean, I
had plenty of opportunities um but but
it that is not where I do my best work,
right? So I think you have to decide for
yourself what is it that motivates you,
makes you happy, keeps you doing this
for for a lifetime. Do do you know what
I mean? And and and you only get one run
at it in in life here, you know? And so,
and if you're going to do your best
work, do the thing that that makes you
the most happy, I think, is and and
that's what I
learned, you know, along the way there,
that coding is part of that, a big part
of that.
>> So then when you were working on C, but
before Typescript, like how did you know
something was missing?
>> I just knew something. I I I I don't
know how I mean it it just I would I
just wasn't feeling as fulfilled with
with with the with only doing the design
part, right? I I I missed the coding.
And whenever I had a chance to write a
little bit of code, I would feel a lot
happier and I go, it's kind of
interesting. I mean, do you know what I
mean? But now I got to go write some
more specs, you know? [laughter]
>> So then, uh was Typescript something you
kind of went towards because you wanted
to write more code? I went towards it
for for many reasons. I mean it wasn't
specifically that to begin with. I I
just found the problem fascinating,
right? I mean because the way Typescript
came about was
actually indirectly through C because
the outlook.com team I think it was
approached the C group and asked whether
we would pretty please productize
something called script sharp. And
script sharp was this thing that took C
and transpiled it into JavaScript so you
could run it in a browser. And I'm like
what? Why? Why would you want to do
that? Why don't you just write the job?
Well, because that way we can get great
tooling. Then we can use Visual Studio
and we can have projects and we can have
type checking and we can have code
refactoring and navigation and we can
write interfaces and people can
understand how this all works. And I'm
like, "Wow,
is JavaScript really that busted?" And
and you're saying like the the way you
want to fix that problem is by
abandoning JavaScript, treating it as an
instruction language, right? And then
having a code generator target it. I'm
like, couldn't we like fix JavaScript?
Wouldn't that be better? Do you know
what I mean? And that's how Typescript
kind of got off the ground, right? It
was like, gosh, there's something here
that's really broken that needs to be
fixed, right? and when it comes to
JavaScript tooling
>> and that's what we set out to do.
>> You know, one thing I thought would be
interesting is in one of the talks that
you gave, you said that you believe that
the speed of your tooling is more
important now because of AI and I want
to hear thoughts on why is that the
case? Well, more and more our workflows
now are are dominated by agents that are
like running away in the background,
right? Right. I mean, like writing code
for you and they make mistakes just like
we do, but they but they but you know,
but you can have as many of them as you
want. So there are like many many more
little workers in the ecosystem writing
much more code, right? And that whole
workflow is like LLMs already have have
performance challenging is and then if
you add like if if you're writing code
in a big project and you have to like
type check it and takes two minutes
every time the LLM writes something. Do
you know what I mean? That's horrible,
right? So So making that go faster is is
a big benefit.
>> Yeah. Absolutely. I guess because it's
it's hammering away.
>> Yeah. Because I mean like like well we
all know LLMs they they like to use GP
and and whatever right but then they're
also smart enough now to realize that if
you're like trying to change this
property called version and like every
other object has a version property. You
can't just grip for version and then go
rename it to something else because like
you're breaking all these other
interfaces that have a version in them,
right? So you got to do semantic search
and the only thing that can do semantic
search is a compiler and so you got to
use the compiler through typically
through LSP through language services or
through our our command line tool that
would give you the equivalent right and
so more and more AI is doing that um and
that means you know compilers run at you
don't you may not even see that they're
running but they're running
and they're doing work on on your
behalf. Yeah.
>> When you talk about AI, it's very
realistic and grounded in the software
engineering. And so I thought it might
be interesting to uh run some common AI
takes that I hear from the internet and
you get your sense of how accurate is
this? What are your thoughts on when or
if it'll be true? Okay. Okay. So the
first one that I've heard um this is
more common at the end of last year is
that you know AI is going to write 90
plus% of the code you know within a
year. Um curious what you think on that.
>> Well for certain classes of apps that
that might like all divide code coded
apps they're writing 100% of the code
right and and there's an awful lot of
that being written.
Are they going to write 90% of the high
quality code on the internet? I don't
know about that. Um so the the thing is
like 90% of what the volume of written
code is just like going like that right
now right because AI writes so much code
so [laughter]
so in a sense that's a self-fulfilling
prophecy right I mean but [snorts] but
but when it comes to like
the super high quality code that no one
has ever written before um it's not
clear to me that AI is going to write
90% of that. So when you think about
cases that AI is not writing all the
code, maybe some examples of the super
high quality stuff, what is that?
>> Well,
I mean it's it's algorithms that no one
has ever seen before, for example, or or
particular solutions like I mean I I
know that AI could not write our
compiler, the TypeScript compiler. It it
just can't. I mean we've tried it. It it
can't do it. Um and I'm not asking it to
either. I mean, I'm not expecting it to
either. Um, but but our compiler is also
not a typical piece of code. I mean,
that's why it's bad at writing it
because it's seen none of it in the
training set. Well, I've seen some
compilers, but not like this one. Not
with these concepts, not with done the
way that that we're doing it, right? And
so, it's just not a good fit there. AI
we we we can't forget that AI is at
heart a big stochastic machine that has
memorized the entire internet, right?
And and is ability and has an ability to
extrapolate somewhat over what it's
memorized, right? Um but if it hasn't
seen it before, it's it's it's not
necessarily going to be all that good at
at doing it. Um it's getting better. I
mean, I'm not saying it's it's not
impressive. I it's it's wildly
impressive what it can do, but I just
think there's a long way still to it's
doing all of it.
>> And I don't know that we ever get there.
I hope we don't because then what's the
point of humans anymore then? I mean,
it's [laughter]
>> Well, I see this take often, too, is um
you know, you won't need to use an IDE
within the year or you don't need to
read the code anymore.
>> Well, good luck to you. I mean, if
you're going to hand AI the keys,
I mean, then all bets are off, right? I
mean, the minute AI you can't convince
AI to fix this issue or this new feature
that you want built, what are you going
to do? I mean, if you don't understand
what what's below, right, that's one
problem. The other problem is, let's say
a user comes to you and goes, your app
just stole my bank account. I'm well,
it's going to sue you. It's not. They're
going to sue you, not the AI. I mean,
it's like at the end of the day, someone
has to take responsibility for what AI
is doing. And if you're giving it the
keys, well, it's on you, you know, but
but I don't know. I personally would not
feel comfortable. I wouldn't be able to
go to sleep at night. I mean, if I
didn't understand what it is that I am
vouching for.
Why is there such a big difference
between this opinion and what I see from
maybe people who work at Anthropic?
>> Well, the difference is all I'm saying
here is not that AI can't do amazing
things. It does it can it does that
every day. But but people love these
like take it all the way to 100%. Right?
And that's where I get off the bus a
little bit, right? I think, oh yeah,
okay, fine. We can get we can get higher
and higher percentage but there still
has to be someone understanding what's
going on and how it's relevant to our
business problem and how it relates to
what our organization is doing and like
I mean there's so many other things that
have to be connected that it's I think
it's wrong to just view it as AI did it
all and we were completely unnecessary
you know and
>> yeah the next one I was going to ask you
was you know three years from now will
AI replace junior software engineers or
what junior software engineers do today.
>> Well, if it does, then how do you ever
get senior software engineers,
>> right? I mean, it's it's like I don't
think so. Well, I not unless you also
believe that you will be able to do your
business three years later than that
without any senior software engineers,
>> right?
>> Because where are they going to come
from? You got to train them. I mean and
but to me I think maybe one thing that
to some extent has happened is that for
certain classes of programmers the the
the pyramid has narrowed at the bottom
right there are fewer people coming in
um and we are wanting them to advance
higher up faster um so that they can get
to this more supervisory role right I
think the the craft of being a software
engineer is definitely changing from
you're you're typing in lines of code to
you're having agents type in lines of
code and you are reviewing the work of
the agents, right? And so so you do more
reviewing, less typing.
Um, and some people love that, you know,
I mean, and and and and really are
fantastic at at that workflow, right?
But it's it's a change in nature of of
what what the job looks like as a
programmer. And this tool that you now
have in a toolbox is having that impact,
right? But it is but a tool and there
are still programmers involved in the in
the process that I firmly believe.
>> It sounds like you enjoy typing out the
code. Would you be less happy if five
years from now
>> I I I for for 40 50 years I have enjoyed
typing out code. Um
I'm actually there there some and so I
will continue to type certain parts of
the code, you know, but there are other
parts of the code that I don't
particularly care to type. I don't care
to type in tests and follow all the
rigor of the particular testing
framework. Heck no. If I can farm that
out to AI, happy me, you know. Um I do
think reviewing has always been harder
for me. It's harder for me to like spend
time on reviewing other people's code
than it is you know writing the code.
But I also think that over time we will
we can make that process of reviewing
code much more ergonomic than it is
today. Right? I mean often today you
just get here's like the list of the
files that were changed and here are the
deltas. You figure it up, right? I mean
AI could help us more there by
explaining what the changes are and and
whatever. And so I I think we're going
to get better at this. It's going to get
more interesting, but it will change the
nature of of the craft.
You said that you've been writing code
for 40 maybe 50 years.
>> What is the hardest piece of code you've
ever written or what's the most
technically challenging thing you've
ever done?
>> There there are so many things that in
their time were challenging, you know.
Um
I mean this last project we worked on,
we knew that like like you know sort of
the easy part was getting the native
code. it's just like just just move it
to this other language, right? But then
this taming this beast called uh shared
memory concurrency and and getting the
compiler to use like as many CPUs as
there are available on your box, right?
That is not a simple problem to solve in
a in a in a compiler because we're all
taught to write sequential stuff, right?
I mean first you do this then you do
this but how do you do all of this at
the same time and then share the data
structures afterwards without anyone
like accidentally modifying the other
guy's data structure and you know how do
[snorts] you in the cases where you have
to do that how do you then synchronize
it and avoid deadlocks and race
conditions and and and whatever right
this it was it was tricky uh there were
some good technical problems uh that
that we licked that I think we can be
proud of you know but
>> what about when hardware was more
constrained earlier in your career Is
there any wacky thing you had to do to
kind of, you know, make it work?
>> Oh, totally. I mean, when I started it
was a like being a programmer was a very
very different thing, right? I mean, I
started out with with 8-bit micros that
had Microsoft basic in ROM, right? And
and the basic interpreter and and you
could buy these books and type in these
Star Wars games or or or whatever. They
were all text, you know, there was just
scrolling and and telling you there's
Klingons over in that C quadrant, you
know, and K4, you know, you got to
whatever, right? Um,
but I got fascinated with understanding
how it was all put together and and got
and and quickly learned how to write uh
assembly code and Turbo Pascal, the
first product I worked on, was all
written in Z80 assembly code. um the
compiler, the editor, the runtime
library, everything was assembly. Um and
writing structured a compiler in
assembly code is like that that was that
was like took a lot of fiddling, you
know, and I mean and you were counting
like okay, I think I can I need to we
need to squeeze this into this EPROM and
then there's only 12K, you know, and I'm
I'm 20 bytes over budget here. Oh, but I
can make this jump this long jump
instead. I could jump to this short jump
and that then jumps to that jump and
then I could save one and that's one
bite saved. Okay. You know, moving right
along. [laughter] I mean, and you you
would you would you you were just like
sitting there and fiddling, you know, it
was it was a craft. It was like
woodworking almost. I mean, it was just
so different from what we do now, right?
Everything is like it's bottomless pits
of capacity and and and and bottomless
pits of expectation from users, right?
Is there a top technical book
recommendation you have for software
engineers? I usually recommend the same
but the the one book that was like the
it book for me when I was younger and
it's called algorithms plus data
structures equals programs by Nicholas V
uh the inventor of Pascal and then later
modular and Oberon and whatever and it's
a
it's a book that is
light on
math and symbolism uh and rich in
instructive examples and good
explanation. ations about how data
structures work. I mean, that's how I
learned about hashts, right? I mean,
like when you're self-taught, you don't
know about hashts. You sort of know
about linked lists, right? And fine. So,
in the original version of Turop Pascal,
all the symbol tables were just well,
they were just linked lists, you know,
or whatever. And then of course as you
had many local variables well you're
you're you're you're going exponential
in search time to you know and then I
read about these hash tables and like
wow what you mean I can like just do
this and then like it's it's basically
like linear lookup time and implemented
and the compilement twice as fast right
I'm like holy cow [laughter]
you know that was useful reading do do
you know what I mean so I was always
like the engineer it like that that I
mean and and understanding how to do
error recovery. He explains that in like
how you construct a simple compiler and
then like you know and it's it's
a it was for me a great book but and now
it's actually like I mean it's just a
big PDF you can download it out there um
it's out of print since 40 30 years.
Yeah. Last question for you is with all
the experience that you have now, if you
could go back to yourself when you just
entered the industry and give yourself
some advice, what would you say?
>> Well, I a couple of things maybe like we
talked about being a team player, you
know, I I I would have probably tried to
educate myself a bit more about that to
to begin with. Um, I think also
one thing in in retrospect is like
don't let people tell you that it can't
be done. When they tell you it can't be
done, it's because they can't do it.
That doesn't mean that you couldn't
possibly do it. Do do you know what I
mean? So, so don't let that discourage
you. Is there a project where you
someone said you couldn't do it and then
you did it and that's how you
>> Well, I think the first thing I worked
on like Turbo Pascal, people were
telling me whenever we told them here's
what we have, they said that can't be
done. That's like nah, you guys are you
full of That's like not possible,
you know. [laughter]
Well, it was. And I didn't know that it
wasn't possible, right?
>> Awesome. Well, thank you for your time.
I really appreciate it, Andrew.
>> You're welcome. No, this is a lot of
fun. Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. This is in the case,
but yeah, we launched on Kickstarter and
we hit our goal within eight hours of
launching. I really appreciate it if you
were one of the people who grabbed one
of the early units. Um, we're now
working on the long journey of building
the tooling now. And so, if you still
want to pick one up, I've left the late
pledges open on Kickstarter, so you can
grab one there. I'll put a link in the
description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next